David A. and Leona G. Bloom papers, ca. 1980-[ongoing]
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
David A. and Leona G. Bloom papers, ca. 1980-[ongoing]
SJA 001
Bloom, David A., 1916-
2.75 linear ft.
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
David A. Bloom (born in 1917) and his wife Leona G. Bloom have been active members of Tucson's business, religious, and social service communities for decades, as well as serving as amateur historians for Tucson's Jewish community. David A. Bloom and his brothers operated the successful retail men's clothing store founded in 1906 by his father, David W. Bloom (called Dave Bloom Mens' Store until 1936 and Dave Bloom and Sons thereafter). The store operated in downtown Tucson at Congress and Sixth for years, later moving to the El Con Mall. His grandparents came to the Arizona Territory in 1869. David A. Bloom has served as president of the Arizona Jewish Historical Society's Southern Arizona Chapter, president of the Tucson chapter of the University of Arizona's Alumni Association, and vice president of Temple Emanu-El. He is the benefactor of the Bloom Southwest Jewish Archives.
Leona G. Bloom (1913-1995) was born in New York City, but she resided in Tucson for over 50 years. In addition to being the benefactor of the Bloom Southwest Jewish Archives, she was very active in community activities and service, including those of Temple Emanu-El, the International Friends, the Organization for Rehabilitation through Training (O.R.T.), Tucson literacy programs, the Tucson Zoological Society, and the Arizona Jewish Historical Society's Southern Arizona Chapter.
Organization
This collection is organized into two series:
Series I: Activity Files
Series II: Scrapbooks
Scope and Content Note
The files in this collection document the involvement of David A. and Leona G. Bloom in service to both the Jewish and non-Jewish communities of Tucson, Arizona. The collection is a particularly good depiction of the community service work of Leona G. Bloom. For instance, there exist here records of her involvement in the University of Arizona's organization International Friends, the Organization for Rehabilitation through Training (O.R.T.), Tucson adult literacy programs, and the Tucson Zoological Society.
There are also present in this collection records which document the activities of both David A. and Leona G. Bloom in Temple Emanu-El of Tucson, the Arizona Jewish Historical Society's Southern Arizona Chapter, the Bloom Southwest Jewish Archives, and scrapbooks documenting the Dave Bloom and Sons store in Tucson.
Access Terms
Bloom, David A., 1916-
Bloom, Leona G., 1913-1995
Dave Bloom and Sons (Firm)
Arizona Jewish Historical Society. Southern Arizona Chapter
World ORT Union -- Arizona -- Tucson -- Correspondence
Tucson Zoological Society -- Correspondence
Jews -- Arizona -- Tucson -- History
Jewish businesspeople -- Arizona -- Tucson
Manuscript text
Biography
Container List
- Series I: Activity Files
  - American Jewish Historical Society. (Box 1)
  - Anti-semitism. (Box 1)
  - Arizona Archaeological and Historical Society. (Box 1)
  - Arizona Historical Society. (Box 1)
  - Arizona Humanities Council. (Box 1)
  - Arizona Jewish Historical Society (Southern Arizona Chapter). (Box 1)
  - The Arizona Post. September 5, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Australia (Jews in) - The Sentinel. (Box 1)
  - (Rabbi Albert) Bilgray Lectureship - Temple Emanu-El, Tucson. (Box 1)
  - Bloom, Alan. (Box 1)
  - Bloom family business concerns. (Box 1)
  - Bloom, David A. (Box 1)
  - Bloom, David W. (Box 1)
  - Bloom, Leona G. (Box 1)
  - Boothill Cemetery (Tombstone, AZ). (Box 1)
  - Canadian Jewish Congress. (Box 1)
  - Capin family (newspaper article). (Box 1)
  - Chicago Jewish Historical Society. (Box 1)
  - Coordinating Committee for History in Arizona. (Box 1)
  - Fenster Gallery of Jewish Art (Tulsa, OK). (Box 1)
  - Ferrin, Mr. and Mrs. M. Joseph (clipping). (Box 1)
  - Frank, Anne (exhibit in Tucson). (Box 1)
  - Free and Accepted Masons of Arizona. (Box 1)
  - Genealogy (Jewish). (Box 1)
  - Goldwater, Senator Barry M. (Box 1)
  - Handmaker Jewish Services for the Aging (Tucson). (Box 1)
  - Indiana Jewish Historical Society. (Box 1)
  - International Friends (organized to assist international students at the University of Arizona). (Box 1)
  - Iola, Rabbi Hyman (Temple Emanu-El - Tucson). (Box 1)
  - Israel. (Box 1)
  - Jewish Archives Committee (oral history procedures). (Box 1)
  - Jewish Colonial Trust. (Box 1)
  - Jewish Community Foundation. (Box 1)
  - Jewish Federation of Southern Arizona. (Box 1)
  - Jewish Historical Society of Central Jersey. (Box 1)
  - Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford (CT). (Box 1)
  - Jewish Historical Society of Greater Washington (DC). (Box 1)
  - Jewish Historical Society of Maryland. (Box 1)
  - Jewish Historical Society of New Haven (CT). (Box 1)
  - Jewish Historical Society of New York. (Box 1)
  - "Jews in the Wild West" (article by Gean Weiss). (Box 1)
  - Judah L. Magnes Museum ("The Jewish Museum of the West" - Berkeley, CA). (Box 1)
  - Kiwanis International. (Box 1)
  - Leona G. and David Arthur Bloom Southwest Jewish Archives. (Box 1)
  - Literacy (articles on). (Box 1)
  - Meir, Golda. (Box 1)
  - Nebraska Jewish Historical Society. (Box 1)
  - The Old Pueblo Club (Tucson). (Box 1)
  - Organization for Rehabilitation Through Training (Women's American ORT) - Continued in next box. (Box 1)
  - Organization for Rehabilitation Through Training (Women's American ORT)- Begins in previous box. (Box 2)
  - Phipps, Brendan. (Box 2)
  - "The Pioneer Jews of Santa Cruz County" (research grant proposal by Judy Margolis). (Box 2)
  - "Profiles of Business Professionals in Our Community" (article from the Arizona Jewish Post- Fall 1990). (Box 2)
  - Rocky Mountain Jewish Historical Society. (Box 2)
  - Sabbar Temple (Masonic temple in Tucson). (Box 2)
  - Schaefer, Dr. John Paul. (Box 2)
  - The Sephardic Educational Center in Jerusalem. (Box 2)
  - Shrine Temples Directory (National). (Box 2)
  - Siegel, Mark A. (Box 2)
  - Southern California Jewish Historical Society. (Box 2)
  - Temple Beth Shalom (bat mitzvah program). (Box 2)
  - Temple Emanu-El (Tucson). (Box 2)
  - Tucson adult literacy programs; 2 public service announcement on reel-to-reel tapes. (Box 2)
  - Tucson Advertising Club. (Box 2)
  - Tucson Better Business Bureau. (Box 2)
  - Tucson Citizen/Gannett Foundation News-Media Relations Conference. October 29, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Tucson Museum of Art. (Box 3)
  - "Tucson/Pima County Community Profile" (instrument of the United Way). (Box 3)
  - Tucson Zoological Society (Continued in next box). (Box 3)
  - Tucson Zoological Society (Begins in previous box). (Box 4)
  - Union of American Hebrew Congregations. (Box 4)
  - United Nations Association of Southern Arizona. (Box 4)
  - University of Arizona (choral music library) (Box 4)
  - University of Arizona (reunion of class of 1938). (Box 4)
  - Washington State Jewish Historical Society. (Box 4)
  - Yad Vashem (The Holocaust Martyrs' and Heroes' Remembrance Authority - Jerusalem). (Box 4)
- Series II: Scrapbooks, 1932-1991
  - Newspaper and magazine advertisements for Dave Bloom Mens' Store (until 1936) and Dave Bloom and Sons (1936 and after). 1932-1949 (Volume 1)
  - Visual items which instruct (new salesmen?) about name brands of mens' clothing and the business practices of Dave Bloom and Sons clothing store. 1956-1960 (Volume 2)
  - Newspaper and magazine advertisements for Dave Bloom and Sons. 1965-1979 (Volume 3)
  - Newspaper clippings, community notices, citations, etc. which document (especially) the community and business dealings of David Bloom; also articles revealing of the overall business climate in Tucson. 1932-1991 [bulk: 1960-1991] (Volume 4)